<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Divine arithmetick illustrated in the right and exact numbering of our days, or, A discourse of the near and continued approaches of death unto every one whatsoever with the same inference and application which the apostle in I Cor. 15 makes from and alike subject, that the knowledge and consideration of these things should exhort people to be stedfast, unmoveable, always abounding in the work of the Lord / by Richard Stafford.</title>
            <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93737</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5117</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42707</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875624</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875624</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152395</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93737)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152395)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2295:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Divine arithmetick illustrated in the right and exact numbering of our days, or, A discourse of the near and continued approaches of death unto every one whatsoever with the same inference and application which the apostle in I Cor. 15 makes from and alike subject, that the knowledge and consideration of these things should exhort people to be stedfast, unmoveable, always abounding in the work of the Lord / by Richard Stafford.</title>
                  <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by E. Whitlock ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Death --  Religious aspects --  Christianity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152395:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Divine Arithmetick</hi> Illuſtrated, In the Right and Exact Numbering of our DAYS.</p>
            <p>OR A DISCOURSE OF The Near and Continued Approaches of Death unto every one whatever.</p>
            <p>With the ſame Inference and Application which the Apoſtle in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. makes from an alike Subject,</p>
            <p>That the Knowledge and Conſideration of theſe things ſhould exhort People to be <hi>Stedfaſt, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmoveable, always abounding in the Work of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY <hi>RICHARD STAFFORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>O that they were Wiſe, That they underſtood this, That they would conſider their latter End,</hi> 
               <bibl>Deut. 32. 29.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>So teach us to number our days, that we may apply our Hearts unto Wiſdom,</hi> 
               <bibl>Pſal. 90. 12.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>E. Whitlock</hi> near <hi>Stationers-hall,</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:152395:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>It is appointed unto Men once to die,</q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 27.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>ALthough Death and Mortality is an eaſie Subject to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe on, becauſe therein ſo very many things do lie open, common and obvious to the Knowledge of all People what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, whether Learned or Unlearned, whither they be Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate or Ignorant, for <hi>The Living know that they ſhall die,</hi> Eccleſ. 9. 5. and unleſs it be to ſtir up your Pure Minds by way of Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, it may ſeem ſuperfluous to write thoſe things which are commonly known already; yet it is ſafe. However, I having already publiſhed to the World many things concerning the State of the Wicked and Sinners, Ignorant and Ungodly, in their Death; and alſo of the Condition of Good Men in their Death, I ſhall here en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to make known what further Thoughts do ariſe in my Mind concerning it, as the ſame do ſpring up from the Book of the Lord the Fountain of Truth, which I have within me by ſeeking and draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out from thence; as alſo from that common Knowledge and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, which the Lord hath given to me as a Creature.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And that knowing the Time, that now it is High Time to awake out of ſleep, for now is our Salvation nearer than when we believed. The Night is far ſpent, the Day is at hand.</hi> Knowing that our Days are continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally paſſing on, one after another, to that State or kind of Being, which ſhall never paſs away, It is certainly <hi>High Time</hi> to rouſe up and bethink our ſelves throughly; for the things of which we have been ſo often fore-told and fore-warned, I mean the things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and ſpoken of in Scripture, which relate unto that God with whom all Creatures <hi>have to do;</hi> and muſt receive from him Bleſſing or Curſing, Happineſs or Miſery: And alſo the things concerning the <hi>World to come,</hi> whereof the Scripture it ſelf, and thoſe inſtructed with the Miniſtry thereof, do all along ſpeak: All this is nearer than when we firſt believed, and draws nearer and nearer day by day, to morrow it will be nearer than to day, and the next day after that nearer than to morrow, and ſo on. We do day by day and night after night approach nearer and nearer to the unſeen things, and to the unſeen State, which is Eternal, for the things which are not ſeen are Eternal. <hi>The Night is far ſpent:</hi> With us ſeverally ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as our Years are, it is evident a great deal of our Life is gone, paſt and behind.</p>
            <p>I liked very well the Expreſſion of a Man which I once heard; when it was told him, ſuch an one was near about forty Years of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152395:2"/> Age; He ſaid thereupon, <hi>That forty Years was a large ſtride towards the Grave:</hi> And truly ſo it is, for it is a ſtriding half way at the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Computation of Man's Life at fourſcore Years. But at the uſual reckoning of threeſcore Years and ten, a Year is three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred threeſcore and five days and ſix hours; which every fourth Year makes three hundred threeſcore and ſix. So that caſt np all this together, it amounts to near about five and twenty thouſand, five hundred and ſixty ſeven days and twelve hours. Here is the exact number of our days, if one was ſure to live ſeventy Years. But how many Thouſands and Millions do come ſhort of it? who either paſs away as the untimely Fruit of a Woman, or dye in their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy, Childhood, Youth, Manhood, or declining Years, before they come to this old Age. So that admitting that any one ſhould certainly come to threeſcore Years and ten, as a thouſand Paces make a Mile, the length of his Journy or Pilgrimage may be reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned up at about twenty five Miles and an half; and it is a going one Pace each day and night; or ſeeing that two ſtrides make a Pace, it is a going two ſtrides towards it, one in the day and another in the night. And thus we who are Inhabitants of Fleſh, do continually Journy or Travel on towards the Land of Eternity. And ſo it is proportionably according to the number of the Days, and Weeks, and Months, and the Years, which the Lord of Life, whoſe are the Times and Seaſons, do lend to every Man here on this Earth. Do not reckon this to be an odd and an unuſual kind of writing, thus to caſt up Numbers, for if ye read in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and in ſome places of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> ye will there find and meet ſo much of this nature, as if the Spirit of God did delight in ſumming and caſting up of Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. So that what we have here mentioned, doth not derogate, vary or alter from that true and ſound Preaching by the Spirit, or at leaſt from thoſe common Aſſiſtances of the Spirit, which are given to every Miniſter of Chriſt, according as he is Faithful and Diligent in the Miniſtration of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>After that the Spirit of God by <hi>Moſes</hi> had caſt up the Number of our days to be threeſcore Years and ten, or fourſcore Years, he goes on to add, <hi>So teach us to number our days, that we may apply our Hearts unto Wiſdom.</hi> One ſaith well, The numbering of our days is the beſt kind of Arithmetick. And truly to me, when I thus caſt up and compute it in my Mind, nothing doth ſo much give me a true, through and lively ſence (if I may ſo expreſs it) even of Mortality it ſelf. Here is the Uſe and Inſtruction of it, To apply our Hearts unto Wiſdom. There is a difference between bare thinking of a thing, and to ſet ones Heart, or to <hi>apply ones Heart</hi> unto it. And ſo it is as to the Sinners and Godly People, for even Sinners do think a little in the General concerning Reiigion, that Heavenly and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Wiſdom; for indeed they cannot help it, and they cannot do
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152395:3"/> otherwiſe, inaſmuch as the Words thereof, and the Sound thereof is gone out to the Ends of the Earth; there is ſo very much Talking and Preaching thereof in this Iſland; there is ſo exceeding much in the Scriptures of Truth, which almoſt every Family hath in its Houſe, that there is none ſo much a ſtranger in <hi>England</hi> who hath not heard of theſe things. What things? Concerning God, and another Life, and the World to come. But as to Sinners and the Ungodly, all this amounts to no more than to a certain Rumour or Report, or a Sound, without a through Knowledge and diſtinct Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of what all theſe things mean; they think of them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are forced to think of them ſometimes, but they do not ſet and apply their Hearts unto them. And ſo it is the very ſame concerning the Numbring their Days, their latter End and Death. Who is there, even amongſt the Ignorant and Ungodly Multitude, yea amongſt thoſe who are moſt Deſpiſers and backward in Nature towards the Miniſtry of the Word, that doth not know in the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral how Old they are; how that time and their Days do paſs away, and how that they muſt Dye at laſt. No Body whatever can be Ignorant of or not know this, becauſe it is Senſible and Evident. But it is too certain again, that they do not for all this, <hi>Apply their Hearts</hi> unto the true Wiſdom. That is, To ſet about it in good Earneſt; for they do not Underſtand what it is, nor Labour after it: But they are Careleſs and Negligent, as pertaining thereto. Whereas Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe the Righteous and Godly do ſo apply their Heart, as to Mind nothing in Compariſon thereto, but they bring all things in Subordination to it.</p>
            <p>Nothing remains in a Man, but what he doth in the Service of God, and for the Good of his own Soul. All his other Acts and Actions periſh in the uſing, and if they do not come under that End, they had much better be not done at all; for whatever is of Sin or Evil, that tends to ſad Account, or Loſs at the laſt Day. And that is Wiſdom indeed, and nothing elſe is ſo, which procures Good unto a Man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſelf, and avoids Evil: Which nothing doth ſo certainly ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, according to his own Ordering and Eſtabliſhment of things (taking in things to come, all one as things preſent) as the Service of God, and the keeping of his Commandments. For if there was nothing elſe therein (as there is Ten Thouſand times more) it appears much better, and more excellent on this Reſpect, That whereas all other things periſh and paſs away, and ſo doth all <hi>the Glory of Man paſs away as the Flower of the Graſs:</hi> But <hi>he that doth the Will of God, abideth for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Religion, our Duty to God, is not only throughout the Book of <hi>Proverbs,</hi> but in ſeveral other places of Scripture, called <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> as particularly in that ſaying of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Wiſdom is Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of her Children.</hi> But alſo it may be Proved, Evidenced and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152395:3"/> to be the only Real and true Wiſdom; and all Deſpiſing, Neglect and Variation from it to be the greateſt Folly. To ſhew or treat of this particularly, and at large would be ſomewhat beſides the preſent intended Subject. But as certain of the Ancients defined the ſum and whole of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> to be a <hi>Meditation of Death,</hi> and that upon this or the like Reaſon, becauſe it would Influence a Man's whole Life and Converſation unto Wiſe and Good things; it being Reaſonable to do thoſe things, whilſt Living, which one ſhall wiſh he had done when he comes to Die. And alſo nothing is ſo much worthy the Concern and Regard of a Wiſe Man, as Death is. It is every ones Prudence to keep off, and provide againſt all Evils whatſoever; and if the World calls them Wiſe, who are ſo much buſied about the getting of Riches or Honour, about the attaining of every little ſeeming Good and avoiding every little Evil that may befal them; much more will he (who is <hi>Wiſe unto Salvation)</hi> be ſo as to the greateſt and moſt enduring things which are to come and will quickly be Manifeſted before us with open Face. If every one is Concerned, how it goes with him now, much more ſhould a Rational and Underſtanding Man look about him, both take thought, and alſo take care, what ſhall become of him, after this vain, ſhort and uncertain Life is Ended.</p>
            <p>Truly this was my manner of doing, from my tender Years, and from my Youth up. As it is written, <hi>That</hi> Iſaac <hi>went out to Meditate in the Field at Even-tide:</hi> So I can Remember that when I was but a School-Boy, and ſo when I went firſt to the Univerſity; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as others of my Fellows and Cotemporaries were all for Play and Company, I would rather chooſe to Walk all alone by my ſelf, and in ſome Solitary place, Meditate partly upon the Works of God's Creation: All which being then new and freſh to my Mind, did Seem to me in the Phraſe of the ſame <hi>Iſaac, To be as the Smell of a Field which the Lord bath Bleſſed.</hi> For I did then perceive Sweetneſs, Beauty and Delight in them, though I do now confeſs, that, having beheld them ſo very often, I have ſince loſt that juſt Wonder and Aſtoniſhment which I had formerly in beholding them: For it hath Diminiſhed, and I have in a manner Ceaſed to be Affected there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. There is ſo much in Cuſtom and Repetition, even of the moſt Marvellons things; that, by continual ſeeing them, they ceaſe to be Marvellous, not but that they are ſo nevertheleſs in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; But as the Edge grows dull by often cutting, ſo through Humane Infirmity and Weakneſs we become dull of Hearing, and dull of Seeing, and dull of Underſtanding, when it is continually up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame Object. But as the ſame <hi>Iſaac</hi> could ſay, <hi>Behold now I am Old, I know not the Day of my Death</hi> Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>7. 2. So when I was but very Young, this was the Subject that I did moſt Think and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate on, though I was then Young, Yet I <hi>did not know the Day of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152395:4"/> my Death;</hi> for ſo much was Senſible and Evident to me, and I had ſo much Underſtanding as then to Apprehend, that Young Boys were Liable unto Death, and ſeveral of them did Die, all one as People of Riper or Declining Years, or in Old Age. I then knew well enough of the ſuddenneſs of Death, and that we always carry the <hi>Root of the matter</hi> about us, even thoſe Seeds of Mortality and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption; we being but like brittle Glaſs, which can be daſhed or broken in a Moment. Yea, when I was a Child, I Spake as a Child, I Underſtood as a Child, I Thought as a Child; I could even then Diſcern that the longeſt Day would have a Night, that though this Life (which is as a Vapour, and continueth not) ſhould be extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up to Youth, Manhood (I am now paſſing this Second Stage of Life) Declining Years, or Old Age, yet at laſt an end would come, <hi>the end is come,</hi> Ezek. 7. 4. And now I can Reaſon this as a Man, that nothing is long which hath an End: But now I call to Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance my Thought, and Searching of Heart, which was in the Days of Old, the Years of Ancient Times, when I was but a Strip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, I did then commune with mine own Heart, and my Spirit made diligent Search, What will become of me, after that this Body which now I carry about me, is laid in the Earth? For I did find even then, that my Spirit would Abide and Liv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> elſewhere, as truly God hath ſhewn this unto me, even from <hi>within</hi> my ſelf, ever ſince I was a Child, and had the leaſt Knowledge of Good and Evil, that there was another Life, and another State which People ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon, and go into, after that they are departed off from this Earth. I was all along, and am ſtill as verily Perſuaded, and as certained of it, as I am ſure, that at the writing theſe Lines, I now Live and Breath. And thereupon Revolving and Pondering many things in my Mind, how that all things here are but vain, little, and paſſing away as a Shadow, and do not ſignifie much, fain would I be happy and ſafe, as to the Succeeding and Eternal State of things, into which my Soul muſt Launched forth out of this Body. So I came at length to be acquainted with the Ways of God; and I have made it my Buſineſs to ſerve him, although it hath been all along (which I deſire to acknowledge in bitterneſs of Soul) accompanied with too many Failings and Imperfections, and comings ſhort of what the Lord hath Required of me.</p>
            <p>It ſhould be a conſtant Rule, that whenſoever I declare and make known my own Experiences, there the Reader or Hearer ſhould confer Notes, and compare it at the very ſame Inſtant with thoſe Experiences of his own; for there is nothing like to this Euperimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Kind of Preaching, when a Miniſter doth inwardly feel what himſelf doth Speak, and Speak out what himſelf doth feel; for we are Fellow Servants and Fellow Travellers; and God, who <hi>Faſhion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Hearts of the Inhabitants of the Earth alike,</hi> Pſal. 34. 15. doth
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152395:4"/> bring all his Sons and Daughters unto Glory, by near the ſame way, in all their ſeveral Generations and Countreys. All of them that ever did, or ſhall come to Glory, they were every one of them, <hi>ſo wiſe as</hi> to <hi>Conſider their latter End.</hi> Saith one of them, <hi>Lord make me to know mine End, and the Meaſure of my Days, what it is, that I may know how frail I am.</hi> And ſo, when we Read the Hiſtory of the Saints, and Servants of God in <hi>Hebrews,</hi> this general Character is given of them all, They confeſſed that they were Strangers and Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims on the Earth, for they that ſay ſuch things, declare plainly that they ſeek a Countrey, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 13, 14. And if they ſeek a Countrey, they muſt be mindful of that Entrance or Paſſage which lets into that Coutrey, which is Death. A Stranger or Pilgrim, are Relative Words, and do Relate unto ſomewhat, to which they ſhould be acquainted, and to ſomewhere they ſhould be at home. Now God is the Father of Spirits, to whom they are Related, and with whom they ſhould be acquainted, according to what is written, <hi>Acquaint now thy ſelf with him, and be at Peace,</hi> Job 22. 21. Though a Stranger is not acquainted and know in ſuch a place; yet others, elſewhere, do know him. And ſo God is acquainted with all Men, as they are his Creatures; <hi>Thou art acquainted with all my Ways,</hi> Pſal. 139. 3. Though alas too many are not acquainted with him. And then mention is made in <hi>Eccleſiaſtes. That Man goeth to his long Home, and the Mourners go about the Streets.</hi> So that he is a Pilgrim all the while he is on this Earth. They are all ſo in Deed and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, but few do confeſs themſelves to be ſo, that is, Strangers and Pilgrims, and declare plainly that they ſeek a Countrey, ſo as not to be Mindful of that Countrey they now are in, no further than barely to Furniſh them with Neceſſaries and Accommodations for their intended Paſſage and Journey; but not to ſit down, or ſettle any Abode or Dwelling-place herein, for a Stranger or Pilgrim doth denote one who is in a Travelling and Moving Poſture, and they are not long in a place; and alſo they have a fixed, certain and intended Place or End, to which they make, or otherwiſe they are but Wanderers. And again it is certain, as long as they are Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling and Moving, if they are ſet aright, every Minute they draw nearer and nearer to their home, or ot the place where they would be. Now whereas many People would willingly ſtay here always, by their Good-will, it ſhall not be ſo, for an the Soul here is in Priſon, ſo it is a Moveable Priſon, or a Moveable Waggon, and the Wheels thereof are always going, until the Appointed Time when they ſhall Ceaſe, and let out the Soul into the Inviſible VVorld. Thus much is ſenſible and evident that the Pulſe is always beating towards its laſt ſtroke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is appointed unto Men once to die.</hi> This Particle, <hi>once.</hi> makes it yet more terrible, and raiſes in it yet greater Thought and ſearching
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152395:5"/> of Heart; for we do more dread, and are more apprehenſive of things which we were never ſenſible of, nor had experienced before. Of ſo many Millions ſince the Creation of Man upon the Earth, we read or hear of but very few that did return again after they were paſſed into the Gates of Death: We read of ſome, as of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> and the Saints that aroſe at our Saviour's Crucifixion and Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. 52, 53. but none are recorded, who gave an exact ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count how or what manner of thing it is to dye, how much Pain they did undergo therein, or how the Bitterneſs of Death did taſte; and how it was with the Soul in the ſeparated State; this is left to every one of us to know and feel. It is as natural a thing to dye as it is to live, for we are appointed to that all one as to be born, or to paſs through a little mean while here: It is only to break that which was liable to be broken before, or to melt down that which was meltable.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe that any one who ſhall hear or read this, were to dye at ſuch a day certain, about a Month, or ſix Weeks, or a quarter of a Year hence; and it is likely enough to be ſome ones Condition, How would ſuch a Meſſage poſſeſs that Soul with fear and ſurprize? God, who hath determined the Times before appointed, <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 26. doth know exactly the day of the Month, and the Year, with the Place, and alſo the manner, with what Sickneſs, or outward Accident or Caſualty each of us ſhall dye, for it is certain to God but unknown to us. So it is of all the Sons and Danghters of Men, although ſome of them are now Healthy, Luſty and ſtrong. If death is not moſt commonly ſudden, yet Sickneſs or Caſualty is always ſudden, which in a week or an hours time will cut down the Tree to the Ground, and fetch out the Soul to give an account for the Deeds done in the Body. The Lord of Life knows all by our Names; and who would now think that ſuch a Perſon and ſuch a Perſon (according as he appoints and marks them out in his own order) ſhall die ſuch a day and in ſuch a place, and of ſuch a Diſeaſe or Accident. This ſame Tongue which hath ſpoken forth his Truths, ſhall one day faulter and be laid flat in my Mouth, and then turn into Corruption, and next to nothing. Theſe very ſame Eyes that ſee at this day, ſhall ſink into my Head, and behold Man no more with the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the World. And theſe Hands which have hitherto handled the Pen of the Writer, ſhall either be tyed and bound up with Grave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloths; or they will be in that fixed and unmoveable Poſture, that there will be no need of tying or binding at all. When we once come into the place of Skulls or dry Bones: There will be then nothing to be ſeen of Perſonal Deformity or Lameneſs, or who in the days of their Fleſh were cloathed with a beautiful, well-coloured, or with a common or ordinary Skin. We know not particularly when this ſhall be, but we know certainly that once it ſhall be, <hi>It is appointed to Men once to die.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:152395:5"/>
            <p>It was Melancholly Tidings of <hi>Samuel</hi> to <hi>Saul, Moreover the Lord will alſo deliver</hi> Iſrael <hi>with thee, and to morrow thou and thy Sons ſhall be with me</hi> (that is in the State of the Dead, as God ſaith in <hi>Ezekiel</hi> of others, that he would bring them down to the People of Old Time) then <hi>Saul fell ſtraightway all along upon the Earth, and was ſore afraid, Becauſe of the words of</hi> Samuel, <hi>and there was no strength in him, for he had eaten no Bread all the day, nor all the night.</hi> Truly ſuch a Meſſage to any of us, would be apt to turn our Stomach againſt Food. It would ſpoil our Supper, and cauſe that we ſhould not ſo well reliſh our moderate neceſſary Eating, if God ſhould ſay to any of us, <hi>This night thy Soul ſhall be required of thee,</hi> Luke 12. 20. Or if we did hear from any one for certain, who is now in the State of the Dead, To morrow thou ſhalt be with me; we alſo would be ſore afraid, and our Souls would as it were before-hand ſhiver within us, before they take flight into the inviſible World; as appears by Poor Malefactors when they come to the place of Execution. <hi>There is no need to ſeek unto familiar Spirits</hi> (as <hi>Saul</hi> did here, which he did not neither, until God had before departed from him) <hi>and unto Wizards that peep and mutter, Should not a People ſeek unto their God? for the Living to the Dead?</hi> Iſa. 8. 19. Which laſt doth ſeem to import, as if it was an incongruous thing to ſeek to the Dead for the Living. But the other is very Proper and Reaſonable, That a People ſhould ſeek unto their God. And truly, If People would ſeek unto their God, who gives his Anſwer now out of his written Word, all one as he did of old Time from his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> they may by that, as alſo by Prayer, know their End, and the meaſure of their days, in near upon as certain and exact a manner, as if they ſhould hear one ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto them from the <hi>Dead,</hi> a Week, Month, Quarter, half a Year or Twelvemonth hence, or ſo many Years hence thou ſhalt be with me, or ſuch a Night of ſuch a Year thy Soul ſhall be required of thee. It hath been already alledged out of the written Word, and by that common Knowledge which God hath given to every Man, as alſo by an exact caſting up of Numbers; and ſo it would be proportionably if it ſhould come unto more Years; The utmoſt Period and Term hath been ſet down, beyond which none doth uſually paſs; and thou mayſt at any time be cut ſhort thereof. Saith one, God therefore kept the preciſe exact day of our <hi>Death</hi> to be uncertain and unknown, becauſe that he would have us think every day to be our laſt. And if thou wouldeſt be certified herein for the Pſalmiſt's Reaſon <hi>That I may know how frail I am.</hi> This laſt thou mayeſt know altogether ſo well as if God had told and repeated unto thee the particular day thou ſhouldſt die. Wouldſt thou know how frail thou art? Why? Thou art ſo frail, that thou art ſubject and liable unto <hi>Death</hi> every day of the Week, yea every hour, and every minute. The Sinner and Ungodly would know this, Becauſe he would <hi>Eat and Drink, for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152395:6"/> to morrow we ſhall die.</hi> Becauſe he would proportion out his Pleaſure and Senſuality accordingly, and come in ſuch a time towards the cloſe of the day, by a Partial, Feigned and Temporary Repentance; for there is hardly any Perſon ſo ſinful, but hath ſome little Hopes, and would do ſomewhat towards the getting the Favour of God, and to go to Heaven if he may be admitted. Whereas, as God has now ordered the Matter, ſuch baſe mercenary and ſelfiſh Souls may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, but God will not be articled with Even Godly and Righteous People have that which ſavours of Men, and of the Fleſhly and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Nature, That if they were ſure to live twenty, thirty, forty or fifty Years longer, they would abate and diminiſh from their former Zeal and Fervency and <hi>Diligence</hi> in the Service of God. But now the Father having kept the Times and Seaſons in his own Power, when he will Summon them to die, and after that to Judgment, the knowledge and conſideration hereof doth oblige them continually to be upon their watch and duty, that whenſoever he cometh he may find them ſo doing. To have their Loins be girded about, and their Lights burning. <hi>And ye your ſelves like unto them that wait for the Lord when he ſhall return from the Wedding, That when he cometh and knocketh, they may open unto him immediately. And if he ſhall come in the ſecond watch, or come in the third watch and find them ſo doing, Bleſſed are thoſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants</hi> (as the four and twenty hours are divided into four Watches, each ſix hours making a Watch, ſo Childhood, Youth, Manhood, Old Age, are the four Watches of the Term of Mans Life) <hi>Be ye therefore ready alſo, for the Son of Man cometh in an hour when ye think not,</hi> Luke 12. 35, 36, 37. We ſhould ſo live, as if every day was to be our laſt day, as if we ſhould die when we go to Bed, or as if we were to be executed and ſuffer death to morrow Morning. So live the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing part of this day and to your lives end, as if certainly this was thy Condition. For though it may be ten thouſand to one that thou ſhalt not actually die within theſe twenty four or eight and forty hours; yet certainly and without all doubt, this is the Caſe and Condition of us all, That e're long this earthly Houſe muſt be diſſolved, and we muſt appear before the Judgment Seat of Chriſt to receive for the things done in the Body, whither they be Good or Bad; ſo that it will be near the ſame thing in God's account, and to thine own Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and receiving, ſeeing that of every day after years of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and diſcretion thou ſhalt be called to an Account, as if thou wert to die for certain before another and ſecond Revolution of the Sun over thine head. How doth any Perſon preſume to live in that Condition in which he is afraid to die? For God will all one enter into Judgment, and call People to an account for the ſame, all one as if they did die in the very Act of ſuch or ſuch ſins. And ſo it is of the ſeveral deeds already done, now in doing, or to be done in the body. Each thing now is juſt done, and then it paſſes into Judgment; for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152395:6"/> we ſhall be called in queſtion and to give account for each days Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions. And if as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Sufficient unto the day is the Evil thereof.</hi> So if we would have Boldneſs and Comfort at the laſt and great Tribunal, we ſhould in the mean while look well unto it, and give heed and uſe our utmoſt diligence and endeavour; that to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poiſe for the Evil of each day, ſome Good ſhould be done, ſomething for the Glory of God, and for the Good of his Church and People, as alſo for the Edification and Advancement of our own Souls in Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs. That it may be pronounced at laſt to our endleſs and unſpeakable rejoycing, when all the days of this Life ſhall come to be rehearſed as they now paſs, though it will be hardly ſaid as to the beſt Saints and Servants of the Lord (for all come ſhort of the Glory of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 23. and of what he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired) ſufficient unto the day is the Good thereof, yet in each day ſomewhat was the Good thereof. Every riſing of the Sun, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the ſame ſets us ſomewhat nearer to the general and final Audit, the great day of Account and Retribution to every one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Works. Yea, ſo doth every minute and ſecond (which is the leaſt reckoning of Time, for as ſixty minutes make an hour, ſo ſixty ſeconds make a minute) and this Time is in continued flux and paſſing on, until it comes to be determined and ſwallowed up in that laſt Period when Time ſhall be no longer. Like as a little Brook or River loſes it ſelf when it ends and empties it ſelf into the great and wide Ocean. As the ſhadow upon the Dial is always moving (though to us it ſeems very ſlow) As the ſtreams of a ſwift running River do continually paſs by; As the little ſands in an Hour-glaſs are for the moſt part running; Yea, This whole ſublunary Creation is made up of change and periſhing things, the World paſſeth away and the Faſhion thereof, and day after day, and night after night, they haſte nearer unto the Eternal and Irreverſible ſtate of things: ſo our ſelves, Men and VVomen, being a part thereof, we are now in the ſame tranſitory and dying Condition, and we do always ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach yet nearer in time unto that ſtate, wherein as to the Earth as now it is, and as to this Mortal Body and outward Fleſh and Blood, as to the manner of this ſhort preſent Life, we ſhall be no more. But exhorting one another, and ſo much the more as ye ſee the day approaching.</p>
            <p>Here the Word of Exhortation is not confined to Miniſters or Prieſts only, but Indefinitely unto all Chriſtians. <hi>And ſo much the more</hi> (Mark, give heed unto and obey that) as ye ſee the Day Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching, even the Day of Death and Immortality of Judgment, and the ſucceeding Eternity. Whether we Eat or Drink, Sleep or Play, Labour or are Idle, the things which ſhall come upon us, make haſte, and do Steal and Approach unto us nearer and nearer.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:152395:7"/>
            <p>As it is written, <hi>Fools make a Mock at Sin;</hi> So there be ſome who make a jeſt of the World to come, whereof the Scripture, and thoſe Inſtructed with the Miniſtry thereof do ſpeak. But it may be Proved and Demonſtrated to ſuch who have but any Sence as to Apprehend that there is a World to come in Reality, whereinto many Millions of Souls have entered already, and our Selves are juſt entering into the ſame. It is not properly another World, but only another part of this ſame World, as a Room of an Houſe. For thus much is manifeſt, even by Reaſon and Perſpective Gla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es, that this Earth where we now in the Body do Inhabit, is the leaſt part of the World, as a Point is unto the whole Globe. This may be known as a Man. And ſo it may be known, becauſe it is ſeen, That the Day of Death to each Perſon is as certain as was the Day of his Birth, and it will as certainly be, as that once was. And this thing of Death, is the Gate or Door which lets and opens into what is called the Future and Inviſible World. And then do appear forth the things contained in Scripture, which are the Objects of our Faith now: But then they alſo will be Actually Preſent, Viſible and Manifeſted before us all one, as the things which we now ſee, han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle and converſe withal. But let ſuch Unbelievers and Scoffers Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what is written, To me belongeth Vengeance and Recompence, Their Foot ſhall ſlide in due time, for the Day of their Calamity is at Hand, and the things which ſhall come upon them make Haſte, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 35. It is commonly-ſaid of Old People, That they have one Foot in the Grave already. But this is certain and true of all People, both Young and Old, even Infants before they can ſtand, or walk on this Earth, that their and our Feet are continually ſliding off from this Stage or Slippery place of the Earth, even when we ſit ſtill, or lye along upon our Beds, we are always ſliding off from this Earth. <hi>In due time.</hi> God hath fixed out, and appointed the time when we ſhall be ſlidden off from this Earth. And the Day of Calamity to Sinners, and to ſuch as have their Portion in this Life (for Death to them is the beginning of Sorrows) is at Hand. It is not juſt already come, but it is within Call, and the things that ſhall come upon them make haſte. Looking for, and Haſting unto the coming of the Day of God, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 12. Whether we do think thereof or not, we do certainly run, yea and fly towards it. But the holy Ghoſt doth Teach and Inſtruct us by this manner of Speech, Looking for, and Haſting unto the coming of the Day of God, that though we do move ſo faſt towards it, yet we ſhould even prevent it in our Thoughts: So we ſhould think more Continually and Earneſtly as we come nearer in time, and ſee the Day Approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>Conceive the Caſe, as ſo it will one time be, that we were upon our Death Bed, and Gaſping for our laſt Breath, and were Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152395:7"/> every Minute or Quarter of an Hour, that our Soul would take her Flight out of the Body, we know not where, What would our Soul (for every Man's Soul is himſelf) then give if ſhe had it, or do, if ſhe were able, to be aſſured of the Peace and Favour of God? How doth the Spirit then contract and gather it ſelf as it were to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and run and make towards the Father of Spirits? Ones firſt Born, Ten Thouſand Rivers of Oyl: Yea, ſhe would then give the whole World if ſhe had it, and if ſuch a thing were poſſible for to obtain his Reconciliation and Loving Kindneſs. Then the ſame Soul that did heretofore Deſpiſe and Diſobey God, is all for Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring of, and Obeying him. But ſhe ſhould have done it before, for now it is too late. But even from the Thoughts of Dying Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, we come to know and diſcern what would have been good for them, and what the Lord did require of them in the midſt of Life, and Happy would it be, and it would be well with them if they had then ſo done. For this is the very top of the chiefeſt VViſdom to do thoſe things whilſt Living, which one ſhall wiſh he had done when he comes to Die: As alſo to refrain from thoſe things, ſuch are Sin and the Pleaſures of Life, as we ſhall indeed wiſh and deſire, that we had abſtained and refrained from, when we come to <hi>Die.</hi> To approach, draw near, and ſtick cloſe unto God. To wait upon him in all his Publick Ordinances (not forſaking the Aſſembling our ſelves together, and that ſo much the more, as ye ſee the <hi>Day</hi> Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching) as alſo in all private <hi>Duties.</hi> To ſerve him with our ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Power, to be a doing of Righteouſneſs and good VVorks, Alms, Mercy and Compaſſion to the very utmoſt of our Ability.</p>
            <p>There is indeed a Bitterneſs in <hi>Death</hi> as <hi>Agag</hi> truly called it. For my part I am not aſhamed to own that I do Vehemently and very much Fear it. This makes me to do Sundry things Pertaining to God and Religion (which I ſhould not do otherwiſe) if hereby I may ſomewhat take off and leſſen from this bitterneſs of <hi>Death;</hi> If hereby I may ſtore up to my ſelf Comfort againſt my dying <hi>Day.</hi> For this Cauſe I am not aſhamed of the Goſpel of Chriſt, nor yet of Preaching it, in (what is called) a Fooliſh and Contemptible manner, as I make it known unto People, in its Simplicity and pureneſs. For I believe that God hath choſen the Fooliſh things of the VVorld, and the things which are deſpiſed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 27, 28. I have already Sufficiently Experienced the ſame, and I have been given to Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand further that this kind of doing hath been, and will be an Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of Loſs as to VVorldly Goods: For more might be allotted unto me, if I would leave off the Preaching and Publiſhing the Truth of the moſt High God. But when I ponder it in my Mind, this ſame Hope of ſtoring up to my ſelf Comfort againſt my dying <hi>Day,</hi> doth with me weigh down all VVorldly Conſiderations or Temptations: And I truſt in the Everliving God, that this ſhall be
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152395:8"/> my Guide unto my dying Day: That I may give up an Account of the Miniſtry which I have received with Joy and not with Grief, for this would be unprofitable for you. The Searcher of all that is in all Hearts, knows that the very Reaſon why I do deſire a full and greater Aſſembly of Hearers, and that my Books and Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings may have a more Univerſal Reception, is chiefly, that I may let down my Net for a greater draught of Fiſhes. For I know, and believe that the more Souls ſhall be converted, Edified or built up in their Holy Faith, by my Miniſtry, it will tend ſo much the more to their own, and alſo my Comfort and Rejoycing, and Crown in the laſt Day. But however, whether more or few will receive it, I ſhall endeavour, by the Divine Grace, to approve my ſelf Faithful in the Miniſtry, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was Faithful in all his Houſe. I mean, not to lead People on (as the manner of ſome is) in a meer outward Profeſſion, as if there was no more than only to come to ſuch a place of Worſhip; Or in a Partial Obedience of the Law, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2. 9 In that deceit ſo common and univerſal amongſt thoſe who call themſelves Chriſtians, of keeping ſome of the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, and neglecting others. Or the Naming the Name of Chriſt, and not departing from Iniquity. Like thoſe who call him Lord, Lord, and do not the things which he ſaith: So there be others of a more Religious ſort, who mightily harp upon the word <hi>Chriſt, Chriſt,</hi> and yet themſelves in the mean while ſhew forth a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erverſe Spirit againſt the Miniſtration of his Word; and they refuſe him that now Speaketh from Heaven through one of his leaſt Members. Againſt all ſuch I do here ſet my Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, according as I have received the ſame from the Word of Truth. God is moſt Glorified when his Servant doth follow the Conduct and Leadings of his Truth, whetherſoever it goes, for this is to follow the Lamb whetherſoever He goes, inaſmuch as the Lamb is the Way, the Truth, and the Life. And ſo I am determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by his Grace to go on, although in the continued Miniſtration, and Succeſſive Outgoing and Emanations of his Divine Truth, Lover and Friend haſt thou put away far from me and mine Acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance into Darkneſs; whether the Multitude or greater part of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple do hear or forbear, receive it or not; and ſo we intirely leave and ſubmit it all to his own <hi>Divine</hi> Majeſty (for God is Judge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) when every Man ſhall receive his own Reward, according to his own Labour, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 8.</p>
            <p>When Jeſus did, by the Grace of God, taſte Death for every Man, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 9. He thereby took away that exceeding bitterneſs in it for all thoſe who will comply with the Ends of his death; which is to die, yea and to be dead unto Sin, and to riſe again unto newneſs of Life. But this doth not belong to the Wicked or Sinners; for in the Hand of the Lord there is a Cup, and the Wine is Red, and it is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152395:8"/> full of mixture, and he poureth out of the ſame; but the dregs thereof all the Wicked of the Earth ſhall wring them out and drink them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75. 8. ſo that the ſame Cup of Death will taſte diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently unto two ſorts of People. The Righteous and the Wiſe will taſte ſome little Bitterneſs therein, wherewith alſo Sweetneſs will be intermingled. Marvel not at this, for I know a Man to whom Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and a kind of Perfume hath aroſe even from the Apprehenſion of Death. But it will be only mixture (wherein the ſowre and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part will make the greateſt Ingredient) and dregs to the wicked of the Earth; for the ſting of Death is Sin, which ſting gives the Pain or ſmart, and it ſtings more or leſs, according as Sin is more or leſs in the Perſon who is to undergo it. So that it muſt be the wiſer and more excellent way to ſtand in awe and Sin not, and to ceaſe from our own Works. By which I mean the ceaſing from thoſe our Works, which do proceed and ariſe from the worldly, fleſhly and corrupt Nature; for all this is our own. The Duty and Obligation hereof, appears from what is written. There re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth therefore a Reſt to the People of God; for he that is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into his Reſt, hath ceaſed from his own Works, as God did from his, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 18. Now Death is the entrance and paſſage into this Reſt; and therefore if we would by this Death be tranſlated into this Reſt, we muſt before this Death ceaſe from our own works, that is to ſay, From all ſuch works which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>avour of Sin, Vanity, or of this evil World. For ſaith another Scripture, <hi>Bleſſed are the Dead which die in the Lord, from henceforth, yea, ſaith the Spirit, that they may reſt from their Labours, and their Works do follow them,</hi> Rev. 14. 13. This is to be underſtood of good Works: For the doing of good Works, is the <hi>Laying up in ſtore for themſelves a good Foundation againſt the time to come, that they may lay hold on eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 18. Such who die in the Lord, did in their Life time before live unto the Lord. And ſuch the Goſpel enjoyns peremptorily, to maintain good Works. <hi>This is a faithful ſaying, and theſe things I will that thou affirm conſtantly, that they which have believed in God, might be careful to maintain good Works: Theſe things be good and profitable unto Men,</hi> Titus 3. 8. For the Spirit of God in the fore-quoted place of the <hi>Revelations</hi> doth pronounce them Bleſſed, becauſe their works do follow them. This Foundation will then ſtand them in ſtead, and they will be Partakers of the Loving Kindneſs and Reward of the Lord for the ſame.</p>
            <p>I have heard of a certain Atheiſt who being asked upon his Death-bed what he then thought concerning Religion, ſaid on this wiſe, <hi>A Good Life and Good Deeds, but all the reſt was Talk and Prate.</hi> In this laſt part of his ſentence he ſpake like an Unbeliever, but as to his foregoing words this may be conceived, that the beſt Life and the beſt Deeds, without the Faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, will never
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152395:9"/> ſave any one. The beſt VVorks, and the beſt Deeds, if they are mingled with any thing of ſelf-Righteouſneſs, or with any Thoughts of Merit, or deſerving for the ſame, they are marred and ſpoiled as to God's preſent Acceptation and future Recompence. They are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like the Girdle that was marred and profitable for nothing, <hi>Jer.</hi> 13. 11. But good and obſervable Truth may be gathered from the former part of his ſaying, <hi>A Good Life and Good Deeds.</hi> For let the Knowledge and Faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt be mixed with the ſame Good Life and Good Deeds. Let this ſame Good Life and Good Deeds be all lifted up and terminated towards God; Let all good Works be done in great Humility, ſelf-abaſement and nothing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Creature, He deſiring that they may be accepted, clothed over with the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and only in and through him; Then all this will, yea it doth yield ſenſible Comfort, and real Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port againſt and in a dying day. For then when the Soul is juſt go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the Body, and moſt wants help whereon to ſtay and fix, It may be truly ſaid to her, there is none like unto the God of <hi>Jeſhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run,</hi> who rideth upon the Heaven in thy help, and in his Excellency on the Sky. The Eternal God is thy Refuge, and underneath are the overlaſting Arms (may this Scripture belong to me, when the ſhadow of Death ſits upon my Eye-lids, and I am juſt breathing out my laſt: I had rather have it than all the Kingdoms, Lands and Riches of the whole Earth for ten thouſand Years, if it was poſſible to enjoy them ſo long.) Theſe good words and comfortable words go on to add) And he ſhall thruſt out the Enemy from before thee (which Enemy is the Devil) and ſhall ſay, Deſtroy them, <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall dwell in ſafety alone, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33. 26, 27, 28. Safety and Salvation is all one in ſignification; and this is ſafety to be ſaved and preſerved from all the Evils of the Inviſible World, to get above and all alone from all the Annoyances of Evil Spirits, as alſo to be freed from all Sin and Temptation henceforward: Let me die the Death of the Righteous, and let my laſt End be like his. But there is no dying the Death of the Righteous, without living the Life of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</p>
            <p>But how much Good Works, or Works of Alms, Mercy and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, eſpecially to the Miniſters and Servants of the Lord, will give and procure unto the doers thereof Comfort and Support in a dying day, we may gather and underſtand from the words of <hi>Paul; The Lord give Mercy unto the Houſe of</hi> Oneſiphorus, <hi>for he oft re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed me, and was not aſhamed of my Chain, The Lord grant unto him that he may find Mercy of the Lord in that day,</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 16, 18. which is the day of Death and the day of Judgment, for then it is that any reaſonable Creature moſt wants the Mercy of God; and the Apoſtle here wrote theſe things by the Spirit, as one that knew the Mind and Will of the Lord; for in what Prayer the Spirit of Truth doth
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152395:9"/> dictate, is included a Promiſe that ſo it ſhall be. And it is the ſame thing as if it did run on this wiſe, That <hi>Oneſiphorus</hi> ſhall find Mercy of the Lord in the day of Death and of Judgment, for that his good Deed which he ſhewed forth unto <hi>Paul</hi> a Priſoner, Miniſter and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of the Lord.</p>
            <p>The Holy Ghoſt doth record of <hi>Dorcas, This Woman was full of good Works and Alms-deeds which ſhe did,</hi> And after that ſhe died, the VVidows ſhewed <hi>the Coats and Garments</hi> (which probably were for the Poor) <hi>which</hi> Dorcas <hi>made, while ſhe was with them,</hi> Acts 9. 36, 39. Theſe things are written for our Admonition, upon whom the ends of the VVorld are come, ſo that this ſhould be yet more drawn forth into Example and Imitation by the Rich People of both Sexes of our preſent Age and Generation, for they muſt ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſicken and die likewiſe, and then they will find <hi>To what Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe was this waſte?</hi> for that ſame Mony which they expended in fine Cloaths, Gaiety and Retinue, or making a Figure in the VVorld, in Gluttony and Drunkenneſs, in Pride, Pleaſure, Prodigality and vain things or ſuch like, <hi>might have been given to the Poor;</hi> and then it would have done themſelves more good, and have ſtood them in more ſtead, than that Mammon of Unrighteouſneſs, or the Riches uſed to the hurt of the Owners. Or they might have thus conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated their Gain unto the Lord, and their Subſtance unto the Lord of the whole Earth, <hi>Micah</hi> 4. 13. In being more willing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute the ſame yet more plentifully towards the Publiſhing and Propagation of his Eternal Truth; which ſeems to be the <hi>Beſt of Works.</hi> For this is a doing Good unto the Immortal Souls of Men, whereas common and outward Alms is only a Temporal Kindneſs unto the dying Body. And alſo that longer remains; as to which the Scripture ſaith, <hi>If any Mans work abide, he ſhall receive a Reward,</hi> 1 Cor. 3. 14.</p>
            <p>To conclude our whole Diſcourſe, This is certain, That we muſt all (both Good and Bad) appear before the Judgment Seat of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 10. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto thee ſhall all Fleſh come,</hi> Pſal. 65. 2. Seeing the caſe is ſo, and there is no avoiding of it, VVhat can be a more forcible Conſideration in the VVorld, ſince that we muſt appear before and come unto a Great God, who is the Great Law-giver, able to Save and to Deſtroy; who doth Good, ſo likewiſe he can and will Puniſh; VVhat manner of Perſons ought we to be in this little mean while between in all Holy Converſation and Godlineſs? VVhat can we do too much to pleaſe and approve our ſelves unto him? To agree with him that was our Adverſary whilſt we are in the way? To do any thing to get his Reconciliation and Favour, his Peace and loving Kindneſs. The only way whereto he hath ſhewed us, is, In beginning, and then continuing and perſevering
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152395:10"/> on to the end, to the day of our ſeveral reſpective deaths, In the true Spiritual VVorſhip and Service, In the Univerſal Obedience of all the words of his Law and Goſpel, and fulfilling all Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; In doing his VVill, and every good VVord and VVork, and to do all this more and more, more diligently and more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly as we come nearer in time and ſee the day approaching.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>Furthermore, then we beſeech you, Brethren, and exhort you by the Lord Jeſus, that as ye have received of us how ye ought to walk, and to pleaſe God, ſo ye would abound more and more,</hi>
               </q>
               <bibl>1 Theſſ. 4. 1.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
